<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Viewer version="1.0">
  <History load="Forio" report="cookie"/>
  <Help title="General Layout" imageSrc="%ITEM_ROOT%/help/help_general.jpg">The screen is divided into two main sections, navigation on the left, and a content area on the right. Clicking on the menu items will display the relevant content on the right.</Help>
  <Help title="Navigation" imageSrc="%ITEM_ROOT%/help/help_navigation.jpg">The main navigation is on the left of the tutorial screen; clicking through the menu items sequentially will bring up the next topic to review. Clicking the arrows to the left of the menu items will open those items. At the bottom of the menu area, Up and Down buttons allow you to page sequentially through the tutorial. At the far left of the menu area, green check marks will appear next to the section or page when you have viewed it.</Help>
  <Help title="Content Area" imageSrc="%ITEM_ROOT%/help/help_content.jpg">On the right of the tutorial screen is the content area, which contains text, graphics, animation, and exercises. Each page might display one of these or some combination of them.  More details about specific content area items are listed below.</Help>
  <Help title="Breadcrumbs" imageSrc="%ITEM_ROOT%/help/help_breadcrumbs.jpg">At the top of the content area, navigable Breadcrumbs will display showing your current location in the tutorial. The deeper you drill into any one section, the more breadcrumb links will appear that show you where you are relevant to the top level of the tutorial. Each Breadcrumb is labeled using the relevant section or page name. Clicking on any of these items will bring you to that location in the tutorial.</Help>
  <Help title="Top Icons" imageSrc="%ITEM_ROOT%/help/help_top_icons.jpg">At the top right of the tutorial, you will find a row of buttons. From right to left, these are: Help, Briefcase, Glossary, and Print.</Help>
  <Help title="Help" imageSrc="%ITEM_ROOT%/help/help_help_icon.jpg">The Help screen provides information on the structure and function of this tutorial. Click on this icon to see additional detail about any of the features you see onscreen.</Help>
  <Help title="Briefcase" imageSrc="%ITEM_ROOT%/help/help_briefcase_icon.jpg">The Briefcase contains supporting documentation and additional, downloadable files that you will need or find helpful for the tutorial. At certain points in the tutorial, the text will instruct you to retrieve a particular file from the Briefcase. Also, clicking on the Briefcase icon at any time will allow you access to all of these files.</Help>
  <Help title="Glossary" imageSrc="%ITEM_ROOT%/help/help_glossary_icon.jpg">Clicking on the Glossary icon will display the complete glossary for the tutorial. Additionally, you can click on the blue underlined terms within the text on a page to see a specific glossary definition.</Help>
  <Help title="Print" imageSrc="%ITEM_ROOT%/help/help_print_icon.jpg">Clicking on the Print icon presents you with the option to print the current module, or the entire tutorial. Please note that this printed version contains no graphics and no images of any animations.</Help>
  <Help title="Page Navigation" imageSrc="%ITEM_ROOT%/help/help_page_nav.jpg">For pages with multiple parts, both Previous and Next buttons appear on the tab, as well as a progress indicator to inform you of how many parts there are and which part you are currently viewing.</Help>
  <Help title="Exams" imageSrc="%ITEM_ROOT%/help/help_exams.jpg">To advance from one question to the next, select one of the answer choices or, if applicable, complete with your own choice and click the “Submit” button. You may also skip a question by pressing the forward advance arrow. You can return to “skipped” questions using the “Jump to unanswered question” selection menu or the navigational arrows.</Help>
  <Help title="Reset Exam" imageSrc="%ITEM_ROOT%/help/help_resetexam.jpg">Your course administrator may give you the option to reset your exams or tests.  Once you complete an exam or test, you will see a "reset exam" option.  A message will appear asking, "Are you sure you want to reset this exam?  All results will be permanently deleted."  Choose OK or Cancel. </Help>
<Node id="tutorial"/>
</Viewer>
